let's learn a fascinating fact about an
amazing curve
imagine a circle lying on a flat line
let's label one point on the circle
that's tangent to the line and let's
start rolling this circle over and over
and over again
if we Trace out the path traversed by
the Red Dot we get this curve here
this curve is known as the cycloid and
it will continue forever as long as we
let the circle roll but we can see that
the cycloid is really one curve repeated
over and over and over again so let's
study this one section of the cycloid
and see if we can find something
interesting about that particular curve
so assume that we have a circle with a
radius of R and we label one point right
at the bottom of the circle tangent to
the surface on which we roll
we roll This Circle exactly one full
turn to create one portion of the
cycloid as shown here one question of
interest about this curve is can we find
the area contained underneath the
cycloid and above the line upon which we
rolled that is can we find this area in
terms of the radius of the circle that
we rolled we know that the distance
between the two endpoints of the cycloid
is 2 pi r because it corresponds to the
circumference of the circle we rolled
we can take this circle we rolled and
place it in the middle like this and the
circle covers some of the area it also
splits the rest of the cycloid into two
symmetric pieces on either side
but now we do something interesting we
apply the two-dimensional cavalieri's
principle
to do this we will go along each of the
two symmetric shapes on either side of
this circle and we will take the width
of the shape at a given point and shift
it over to the left as shown here
because we keep the widths the same at
each point and don't change the height
the resulting shape that arises out of
this process will have the same area as
the shape we started with
it might not seem any easier to find the
area of these resulting shapes but now
we can apply another property the
symmetry of the circle if we draw the
lines coming from the center of the
cycloid to the top of these new shapes
we see that because of the symmetry of
the circle this area above the line
matches the missing area below the line
and likewise this happens on the other
side as well
after applying cavalieri's principle and
the Symmetry argument we see that we've
decomposed the area under the cycloid
into a circle of radius R and two
triangles of height 2R and base pi times
r
the area of the circle is pi times r
squared the area of both of the
triangles is also pi times r squared so
the area under the cycloid is 3 times pi
times r squared where R is the radius of
the circle rolled to create the cycloid
this is a truly amazing fact the area
under the cycloid is three times the
area of the circle rolled to create the
cycloid